Guide to the Milbank Memorial Fund Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Milbank Memorial Fund records
1898-2000
1922-1999
MS 845
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
100.25
The records consist of administrative files of the organization, biographical and historical material on the fund, editorial files, press releases, bibliographies on aspects of public health, and specialized reports on individual programs. Fund officers whose biographical material and speeches were collected include John A. Kingsbury, Albert Goodsell Milbank, William H. Welch, and C.-E. A. Winslow. Of particular interest are the records (1922-1934) of the Bellevue-Yorkville Project which contain reports and printed matter relating to one of the three health demonstration projects which the fund supported in the early 1920s. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Milbank Memorial Fund
Conditions Governing Access
While this collection as a whole is available for research, parts of it may be restricted due to law, university policy or fragility. Any restricted material will be noted as such.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Milbank Memorial Fund in 1977, 1978, 1984, 1990, 1991, 1992, and 1995, and 2001. Gift of the New York Academy of Medicine, 2003.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and eleven additions: I. General Papers, 1922-1977. II. Biographical and Historical Records, 1898-1973. III. Bellevue-Yorkville Project Records, 1922-1934.
Scope and Contents
The Milbank Memorial Fund Records span the years 1898-1977 and consist of the minutes and other administrative records of the organization; historical material regarding the fund, and bibliographical papers for fund officers, and miscellaneous material regarding programs. General correspondence and office files were not preserved by the organization, and the manuscript group represents all of the fund's extant records through the early 1970's. The records are organized in three series: GENERAL PAPERS, BIOGRAPHICAL AND HISTORICAL RECORDS, and BELLEVUE-YORKVILLE PROJECT RECORDS.
Series I, GENERAL PAPERS, is organized in four sections: Administrative Records, Commission and Committee Records, Press Releases, and Miscellany. The Administrative Records consist of minutes, proceedings and other records of the fund's Annual Conferences, Board of Directors and administrative subdivisions. The records are organized alphabetically by subdivision; material for each subdivision is filed chronologically. The records of the Annual Conferences (proceedings, 1943-1946 and 1950-1969), Board of Directors Quarterly Meetings (agenda books, 1954-1977), and Technical Board (minutes, 1922-1977) are the most complete.
The Commission and Committee Records section contains proceedings of the International Macy Conference of the Present State and Future of Public Health (1973) and of the fund-sponsored Commission for the Study of Higher Education for Public Health (1973-1974). The material for the latter conference also contains one box of survey reports which include identifiable personal information on students enrolled in schools of public health; this material is restricted and is not available for research until the year 2049.
The remainder of the Commission and Committee Records is made up of copies of material prepared by the fund for submission to two different Congressional committees investigating tax exempt foundations. The material for both committees includes financial data regarding fund income and expenditures and other information.
The Press Releases section of Series I contains all of the one hundred and twelve numbered news releases issued by the fund (often in multiple versions) between 1923 and 1956, and sixteen of the original one hundred and forty-seven clipping books maintained by the fund through 1963. Indexes for both the news releases and the clipping books are filed at the beginning of the section.
Series II, BIOGRAPHICAL AND HISTORICAL RECORDS, is organized in two sections, Biographical Records and Historical Records. The series spans the years 1898 to 1973, although the bulk of the records dates from the 1920's and 1930's. The first section contains a general biographical folder for fund officers (filed at the beginning of the series) and more extensive files for selected officers which are filed alphabetically by personal name. The section contains a variety of documentary material, including biographical sketches, photographs, newsclippings and occasional correspondence. The files for Albert G. Milbank and C.-E.A. Winslow are of special value.
The Historical Records section is arranged chronologically and contains a variety of brief histories, historical sketches, and summaries of activities produced by the fund. It also includes occasional documents.
Series III, BELLEVUE-YORKVILLE PROJECT RECORDS, contains reports and print material for one of the three health demonstrations which the Milbank Memorial Fund supported in the early 1920s. The records span the years 1922 to 1934 and are arranged chronologically.
The Milbank Memorial Fund Records were donated to Yale University Library in 1977 and 1978 by the fund. The records are part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection, and the collection includes the papers of several fund officers, including those of Leroy E. Burney, president from 1971 to 1977 (Ms. Group no. 842).
Biographical / Historical
The Milbank Memorial Fund was established and endowed by Elizabeth Milbank Anderson as a memorial to her parents, Jeremiah and Elizabeth Lake Milbank. Incorporated in New York on April 3, 1905, as the Memorial Fund Association, the organization was chartered "to improve the physical, mental and moral condition of humanity and generally to advance charitable and benevolent objects." The organization's name was changed to the Milbank Memorial Fund in 1921.
The Milbank Memorial Fund has focused its activities in the field of public health, and has had a significant impact in promoting reform in the organization and delivery of health care. Historically the Milbank Fund has operated by identifying and concentrating on successive problem areas in public health. As alternative funding has become available to support work in a given area, the organization has moved on to a new emphasis. In the early 1920s the fund devoted most of its resources to medical care and health delivery systems, funding several health demonstration projects in urban and rural areas of New York State. In 1928 it began studying the relationship between population problems and public health, and it continued to support demographic research for four decades, longer than any other program.
In the 1930s attention was turned to nutrition and the hygiene of housing. In the 1940s and 1950s the Milbank Fund's program expanded to include the epidemiology of chronic disease and especially the development and appraisal of mental health services. In the 1960s the organization focused on promoting the development throughout the western hemisphere of young medical educators in the areas of social and preventive medicine. During the 1970s the fund shifted emphasis to health services consumerism and to the acquisition and application of knowledge about more effective utilization of health services.
For additional information on the Milbank Memorial Fund, see Series II, BIOGRAPHICAL AND HISTORICAL RECORDS.
Health facilities; Health maintenance organizations; Medical care; Medicine; Public health; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Kingsbury, John Adams, 1876-1956; Milbank, Albert G. (Albert Goodsell), 1873-1949; Welch, William Henry, 1882-1941; Winslow, C.-E. A. (Charles-Edward Amory), 1877-1957; Milbank Memorial Fund
- General Papers, 1922-1977; Series I; 9 linear feet (23 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  GENERAL PAPERS is organized in four sections: Administrative Records, Commission and Committee Records, Press Releases, and Miscellany. The first two sections are arranged chronologically in subdivisions and the third is arranged chronologically by type of material.
  - Administrative Records
    - Advisory Council
      - Minutes, proceedings and guest list, 1922 November 16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Committee lists, 1922-1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Annual dinner programs, 1922-1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Program, notes and attendance lists, 1923 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Dinner meeting speech transcripts and extracts, 1924 November 20 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - List of members, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Annual conference programs, 1925, 1927-1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Annual Conference
      - Programs, 1936-1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Dinner meeting proceedings, 1943-1944,1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Programs, 1946-1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Symposium on Biological Aspects of Mental Health and Disease: proceedings, 1950 November 13-16 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Dinner meeting proceedings, 1950-1955 (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
      - Programs, 1954-1967 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Dinner meeting proceedings, 1956-1958, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
      - Dinner meeting proceedings, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Round Table Conference on Medical Education in Latin America
        - Background papers, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 19)
        - Program, list of participants and opening remarks, 1963 September 30-October 4 (Box 3, Folder 20)
        - Proceedings, vol. I, 1963 September 30 (Box 3, Folder 21)
        - Proceedings, vol. II, 1963 October 1 (Box 3, Folder 22)
        - Proceedings, vol. III, 1963 October 2 (Box 3, Folder 23)
        - Proceedings, vol. IV, 1963 October 3 (Box 4, Folder 24)
        - Proceedings, vol. V, 1963 October 4 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - Dinner meeting proceedings, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - Sixtieth anniversary conference proceedings, 1965 April 5-7 (Box 4, Folder 27)
      - Dinner meeting proceedings, 1967 October 17, 1969 October 29 (Box 4, Folder 28)
      - Round Table on Current Research on Fertility and Family Planning in Latin America (Box 4)
        - Proceedings, 1967 October 17-1967 October 19 (Box 4, Folder 29-31)
      - Round Table on Demographic Aspects of the Black Community
        - Proceedings, vol. I, 1969 October 28 (Box 5, Folder 32)
        - Proceedings, vol. II, 1969 October 29 (Box 5, Folder 33)
        - Proceedings, vol. III, 1969 October 30 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Board of Directors Quarterly Meetings
      - Agenda books, 1954-1957 (Box 5, Folder 35-38)
      - Agenda books, 1958-1963 (Box 6, Folder 39-44)
      - Agenda books, 1964-1968 Mar, May, Oct, December (Box 7, Folder 45-50)
      - Agenda books, 1969 Mar, May, Oct, December (Box 8, Folder 51-52)
      - Agenda books, 1970 Mar, May, Oct, December (Box 8, Folder 53-54)
      - Agenda books, 1971 Mar, May, Oct, December (Box 8, Folder 55-56)
      - Agenda books, 1972 Mar, May (Box 8, Folder 57)
      - Agenda books, 1972 Oct, December (Box 9, Folder 58)
      - Agenda books, 1973 Mar, May, Oct, December (Box 9, Folder 59-60)
      - Agenda books, 1974 Mar, May, Oct, December (Box 9, Folder 61-62)
      - Agenda books, 1975 Mar, May, Oct, December (Box 9, Folder 63-64)
      - Agenda books, 1976 Mar, May (Box 9, Folder 65)
      - Agenda books, 1976 Oct, December (Box 10, Folder 66)
      - Agenda books, 1977 Mar, May, Oct, December (Box 10, Folder 67-68)
    - Boards of Counsel
      - Committee lists, 1923-1930 (Box 10, Folder 69)
      - Annual dinner meeting programs, 1929-1937 (Box 10, Folder 70)
    - Technical Board
      - Minute books: index, Circa 1975 (Box 10, Folder 71)
      - Conference Committee minutes, 1922 (Box 10, Folder 72)
      - Minute books 1-4, pp. 1-302, 1922-1925 (Box 10, Folder 73)
      - Conference Committee minutes, 1923-1926 (Box 10, Folder 74-76)
      - Minute books 1-4, pp. 303-636, 1926-1928 (Box 11, Folder 77)
      - Minute books 1-4, pp. 637-908, 1929-1931 (Box 11, Folder 78)
      - Minute books 1-4, pp. 909-1155, 1932-1935 (Box 11, Folder 79)
      - Minute books 1-4, pp. 1156-1355, 1936-1940 (Box 11, Folder 80)
      - Minutes, 1939-1941 (Box 11, Folder 81-83)
      - Minute books 1-4, pp. 1356-1573, 1941-1946 March (Box 11, Folder 84)
      - Minutes, 1942-1946 (Box 12, Folder 85-89)
      - Minute book 5, pp. 1574-1921, 1946 April-1952 (Box 12, Folder 90)
      - Minutes, 1947-1953 (Box 12, Folder 91-97)
      - Minute book 6, pp. 1922-2230, 1953-1958 (Box 12, Folder 98)
      - Minutes, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 99)
      - Minutes, 1955 March-Sep, December (Box 13, Folder 100-101)
      - Minutes, 1956 March May, June-December (Box 13, Folder 102-103)
      - Minutes, 1957-1959 (Box 13, Folder 104-106)
      - Minute book 7, pp. 2231-2528, 1959-1966 (Box 13, Folder 107)
      - Minutes, 1960-1963 (Box 13, Folder 108-111)
      - Minutes, 1964-1967 (Box 14, Folder 112-115)
      - Minute book 8, pp. 2529-2662, 1967-1974 (Box 14, Folder 116)
      - Minutes, 1968-1971 (Box 14, Folder 117-120)
      - Minutes, 1972-1977 (Box 14, Folder 121-126)
  - Commission and Committee Records
    - Commission for the Study of Higher Education for Public Health
      - Schedule of meetings and news releases, 1972-1975 (Box 14, Folder 127)
      - Transcript of proceedings, 2nd meeting, 1973 January 26-1973 January 27 (Box 14, Folder 128-129)
      - Transcript of proceedings, 3rd meeting, 1973 April 5-1973 Ape 7 (Box 15, Folder 130-132)
      - Transcript of proceedings, 4th meeting, 1973 October 3-1973 October 5 (Box 15, Folder 133-135)
      - Transcript of hearing, 1973 November 4, 7 (Box 16, Folder 136)
      - Transcript of proceedings, 5th meeting, 1973 December 6-1973 December 8 (Box 16, Folder 137-139)
      - Transcript of proceedings, 6th meeting, 1974 February 20 (Box 16, Folder 140)
      - Transcript of proceedings, 6th meeting, 1974 February 21-1974 February 22 (Box 16, Folder 141-142)
      - Ad Hoc Committee on Financial Aspects: transcript of proceedings, 1974 May 2 (Box 17, Folder 143)
      - Transcript of proceedings, 1974 May 23 (Box 17, Folder 144)
      - Transcript of proceedings, 7th meeting, 1974 May 29-1974 May 31 (Box 17, Folder 145-147)
      - Transcript of proceedings, 8th meeting, 1974 September 29 (Box 17, Folder 148)
      - Transcript of proceedings, 8th meeting, 1974 September 30-1974 October 1 (Box 18, Folder 149-150)
      - Survey of schools of public health: survey letter, reports and related material (restricted), 1974 (Box 19, Folder 151)
        Conditions Governing Access
        Student records in box 19 are restricted until January 1, 2051.
      - Transcript of proceedings, 9th meeting pp. 1-303, 1975 February 6 (Box 20, Folder 152)
      - Transcript of proceedings, 9th meeting pp. 304-597, 1975 February 7 (Box 20, Folder 153)
    - International Macy Conference of the Present State and Future of Schools of Public Health
      - Transcript of proceedings, pp. 1-592 (not paginated sequentially), 1973 October 24-30 (Box 20, Folder 154)
      - Transcript of proceedings, pp. 601-1173, 1973 October 24-30 (Box 20, Folder 155)
    - United States Congress, House Select Committee on Small Business
      - Articles of incorporation and bylaws, 1921-1922, 1960-1966 (Box 21, Folder 156)
      - Exemption application and related documents, 1941-1942 (Box 21, Folder 157)
      - Balance sheet and related material, 1961 (Box 21, Folder 158)
      - Lists of brokerage houses and securities, 1961 (Box 21, Folder 159)
      - Correspondence and newsclippings, 1961-1963, undated (Box 21, Folder 160)
      - Report, 1962 December 31 (Box 21, Folder 161)
        General note
        See also: OVERSIZE
    - United States Congress, House Special Committee to Investigate Tax Exempt Foundations and Comparable Organizations
      - Print material including House bills, 1948, 1953-1956 (Box 21, Folder 162)
      - Questionnaire submitted by committee to Milbank with Milbank's answers, 1952 (Box 21, Folder 163)
      - Working papers re: report to committee, 1952-1954 (Box 21, Folder 164)
      - Testimony texts (Arthur Adams, Pendleton Herring, James S. Simmons), 1952-1954 (Box 21, Folder 165)
      - Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 21, Folder 166)
      - Report prepared by Milbank for committee, parts 1-3, 1953 December 30, 1954 January 20, 1954 February 24 (Box 21, Folder 167)
      - Committee report, 1954 December 16 (Box 21, Folder 168)
      - Working papers re: report to committee, 1954 (Box 21, Folder 169)
  - Press Releases
    - Clippings and news releases: Lists and indexes, 1924-1948, undated (Box 22, Folder 170)
    - News releases, 1-10, 1923-1924 (Box 22, Folder 171)
    - News releases, 11-25, 1924-1926 (Box 22, Folder 172)
    - News releases, 26-37, 1927-1929 (Box 22, Folder 173)
    - News releases, 38-44, 1930 (Box 22, Folder 174)
    - News releases, 45-59, 1930-1931 (Box 22, Folder 175)
    - News releases, 60-70, 1931-1933 (Box 22, Folder 176)
    - News releases, 71-80, 1933-1934 (Box 22, Folder 177)
    - News releases, 81-90, 1934 (Box 22, Folder 178)
    - News releases, 91-96, 1935-1936 (Box 22, Folder 179)
    - News releases, 97-101, 1936-1938 (Box 22, Folder 180)
    - News releases, 102-112, 1939-1956 (Box 22, Folder 181)
    - Miscellaneous news releases, 1925-1972, undated (Box 22, Folder 182)
    - Clipping book no. 4, 1924 June 17 (Box 22, Folder 183)
    - Clipping book no. 67, 1932 June 22 (Box 22, Folder 184)
    - Clipping book no. 81, 1934 March 14-15 (Box 22, Folder 185)
    - Clipping book no. 83, 1934 April 6 (Box 22, Folder 186)
    - Clipping book no. 91, 1935 January 28 (Box 22, Folder 187)
    - Clipping book no. 92, 1935 March 27-28 (Box 23, Folder 188)
    - Clipping book no. 93, 1935 April 20 (Box 23, Folder 189)
    - Clipping book no. 97, 1936 March 26-27 (Box 23, Folder 190)
    - Clipping book no. 100, 1937 April 29-30 (Box 23, Folder 191)
    - Clipping book no. 519, a-1, 1925-ca. 1960 (Box 23, Folder 192)
    - Clipping book no. 519, m, 1925-ca. 1960 (Box 23, Folder 193)
    - Clipping book no. 519, n-w, 1925-ca. 1960 (Box 23, Folder 194)
    - Clipping book no. 534, 1934-1961 (Box 23, Folder 195-197)
    - Clipping book no. 546, 1950-1963 (Box 23, Folder 198)
    - Unnumbered clipping book, 1962 February (Box 23, Folder 199)
    - List of MMF publications, undated (Box 23, Folder 200)
  - Miscellany
    - Print material, 1928, 1961, 1964 (Box 23, Folder 201)
    - Contracts with publishers, 1931-1961 (Box 23, Folder 202)
- Biographical and Historical Records, 1898 -1973; Series II; 3 linear feet (6 boxes)
  BIOGRAPHICAL AND HISTORICAL RECORDS is organized in two sections: Biographical Records and Historical Records. The first section is arranged alphabetically and the second is arranged chronologically.
  - Biographical Records
    - A - W: biographical material (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Austin, Chellis A.: biographical sketch and clippings, 1929-1930, undated (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Baehr, George: biographical sketch and photograph, 1963, undated (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Biggs, Hermann M.: speech and memorial tributes, 1921-1934 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Boudreau, Frank George: biographical sketch and photograph, 1943, 1949, 1970-1973 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Farrand, Livingston: biographical sketch, clippings and photograph, 1929, 1939, undated (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Folks, Homer: speeches and reprints, 1923-1934 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Folks, Homer: speeches, biographical sketch and reprints, 1936-1959, undated (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Fox, T. F.: correspondence, 1959-1962 (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - Kingsbury, John A.
      - Speeches, 1898-1927 (Box 24, Folder 10-12)
      - Speeches and Advisory Council proceedings, 1928-1932 (Box 24, Folder 13)
      - Speeches, 1933-1934 (Box 24, Folder 14)
      - Reprints, biographical sketch and photographs, 1937-1938, 1956, undated (Box 24, Folder 15)
    - McCleary, George F.: speeches and reprints, 1930, 1933, undated (Box 25, Folder 16)
    - Milbank, Albert Goodsell
      - Correspondence and speech outlines, 1931 December-1932 May (Box 25, Folder 17)
      - Article, "Socialized Capitalism" and related correspondence, 1932 June 1-25 (Box 25, Folder 18)
      - Correspondence re: "Socialized Capitalism", 1932 June 27-30 (Box 25, Folder 19)
      - Correspondence, 1932 July-December (Box 25, Folder 20-21)
      - Article, "Socialized Individualism" and related correspondence, 1933 January-March 16 (Box 25, Folder 22)
      - Correspondence re: "Socialized Individualism" and unemployment insurance, 1933 March 17-April (Box 25, Folder 23)
      - Speeches and reprints, 1934-1939 (Box 25, Folder 24)
      - Correspondence, speeches and clippings, 1940-1944 (Box 25, Folder 25)
      - Correspondence and speeches re: Welfare Council of New York dinner and award, 1945 (Box 25, Folder 26)
      - Correspondence, 1946-1948 (Box 25, Folder 27)
      - Biographical sketch, memorial tribute and correspondence, 1949 (Box 25, Folder 28)
      - Correspondence and biographical material, 1950-1951 January-April (Box 25, Folder 29-30)
      - Biographical material, 1951 Jul, 1952-1953, 1956 (Box 26, Folder 31-32)
      - Speeches and photograph, undated (Box 26, Folder 33)
    - Morris, Roland Sletor: biographical sketch, 1945 (Box 26, Folder 34)
    - Parran, Thomas: print material and biographical sketch, 1927-1941, 1962-1968 (Box 26, Folder 35)
    - Payne, Anthony M.-M.: speech, correspondence and biographical sketch, 1964, 1970, undated (Box 26, Folder 36)
    - Root, Elihu: speech and clippings, 1924-1931, 1962 (Box 26, Folder 37)
    - Ruhland, George C.: biographical sketch, and correspondence, 1924, 1958, undated (Box 26, Folder 38)
    - Sheldon, Edward: biographical sketch and photograph, 1929 (Box 26, Folder 39)
    - Sydenstricker, Edgar: reports, biographical material and photographs, 1923-1936, 1973, n.d (Box 26, Folder 40)
    - Welch, William H.
      - Speeches and print material, 1924-1930 (Box 26, Folder 41)
      - Photographs, 1930 (Box 26, Folder 42)
      - 80th birthday report and photographs, 1931 (Box 26, Folder 43)
      - Notes and memorial tributes, 1932-1934, undated (Box 27, Folder 44)
      - Correspondence re: admission to the Hall of Fame for Great Americans at New York University, 1965 (Box 27, Folder 45)
      - Photographs, undated (Box 27, Folder 46)
    - Winslow, C.-E. A.
      - Correspondence re: studies conducted, 1929-1931 (Box 27, Folder 47)
      - Correspondence, 1932-1933 (Box 27, Folder 48)
      - Correspondence re: Bellevue-Yorkville Health Demonstration, 1934-1936 (Box 27, Folder 49)
      - Correspondence, 1937-1939 (Box 27, Folder 50)
      - Correspondence and conference proceedings, 1940 (Box 27, Folder 51)
      - Correspondence, 1941-1942 (Box 27, Folder 52)
      - Correspondence, 1943-1946 (Box 27, Folder 53)
      - Correspondence and reports, 1947 (Box 27, Folder 54)
      - Correspondence, 1948, 1951-1954 (Box 27, Folder 55)
      - Biographical sketch and correspondence, 1956-1958 (Box 27, Folder 56)
      - Reprints and correspondence re: biography, 1960-1963, undated (Box 27, Folder 57)
    - Miscellany: stories for speeches, unidentified photographs and biographical material, 1927-1945, undated (Box 27, Folder 58)
      General
  - Historical Records
    - Correspondence re: Community Service Society of New York, 1913 March 5 (Box 28, Folder 59)
    - Initial report and extract from report, 1921 May 11 (Box 28, Folder 60)
    - Correspondence and citation re: Mrs. Elizabeth Milbank Anderson's will, 1922, 1930 (Box 28, Folder 61)
    - Memorial Choir, Princeton University Chapel: dedication service booklet, print and related material, 1924, 1928 October-November (Box 28, Folder 62)
    - Historical sketches and summaries, 1927-1934, 1969 (Box 28, Folder 63)